我现在站在阿尔卑斯山深处一条巨大的隧道里。
I'm currently standing in a massive tunnel deep beneath the Alps.
建成之后，这项令人叹为观止的工程
When it's finished, this incredible feat of construction
将延伸超过50公里，
is going to stretch more than 50 km
把欧洲两个大国拉得更近。
and bring two major European countries closer together.
因为这条隧道是一条新铁路线的主体区段，
It's because the tunnel forms the main section of a new railway
建成后两地之间的行程时间将直接缩短一半。
that will literally cut journey times between these two places in half.
再过几年，它将成为全球最长的单洞铁路隧道。
In a few years from now, it'll become the longest single rail tunnel >> >> in the world.
但穿山建铁路，到底是怎么做到的？
But how exactly do you build a train line through a mountain range?
我来到了世界上最大的建设工地之一，
>> >> I've come to one of the world's biggest construction projects
亲眼见证施工团队是如何完成这项壮举的。
to see how teams are pulling it off.
我们正在穿越一座山的中心。
We're digging through the middle of a mountain.
我还想探寻这个工程将带来的巨大影响——
>> >> And to discover the incredible impact it's going to have,
不只是对两侧国家，
not just for the countries on either side,
对整个欧洲大陆也一样。
but for this wider continent, too.
哇！
Woah!
看看这里。
Look at this.
这真的是我迄今为止挖掘得最深的一次报道。
>> >> This is quite literally my deepest dive yet.
这是地球上最宏大的超级工程之一。
It's one of this planet's biggest mega builds.
话说我现在正在法国和意大利之间进行一次公路旅行。
>> >> So, I'm currently on a little road trip between France and Italy.
我正在驾车
I'm driving
从里昂出发，那座城市就在我身后。
from Lyon, which is back there behind me.
你可以在地图上看到它的位置。
You can see it here on the map.
我们要沿着这条路一直开到
And we're going to be going along this road all the way here
意大利的都灵。
to Turin in Italy.
现在，那条路是两地之间
Now, that road is the quickest and easiest way currently
最快、最便捷的通行方式。
to get between these two places.
但也没那么简单，
But it's not straightforward,
因为地图上看不出来——
because what you can't see on this map
这两座城市之间横亘着巍峨的阿尔卑斯山。
is that sitting between these two cities are the mighty Alps.
别误会，这段路风景真的很美。
Now, don't get me wrong. It is a beautiful drive.
但开车要花大约4个小时，
But it takes you about 4 hours,
坐火车也差不多。
and it would be the same if you were to go by train.
不过，这种状况不会持续太久了。
However, it's not going to stay like that for much longer,
建设团队正在这道天然国境线之下修建一条新铁路，
because construction teams are now working on a new railway underneath this natural border.
靠的是一条破纪录的隧道。
And they're doing it with a record-breaking tunnel.
法国和意大利是全球最大的经济体之中的两个，
France and Italy are two of the largest economies on the planet,
而且紧紧相邻。但
and they're situated right next to each other. But
尽管如此，尽管两国都是欧盟成员，
despite that, and the fact they're both part of the EU,
人员和货物的往来并不那么顺畅。
moving people and goods between them isn't exactly straightforward.
罪魁祸首就是那片山脉。
And it's because of those mountains.
在那里修路已经很难了，
It's a difficult place to build a road,
更别说铁路了，所以意法两国之间
let alone a railway, which is why 92% of all freight movement
92%的货运都是靠卡车完成的。
between Italy and France is done by truck.
我想我不用多解释——公路运输既比铁路
Now, I probably don't need to tell you that road transportation
更污染环境，又更慢。
is both worse for the environment and slower than going by train.
所以，这个问题终于有人要正式解决了。
So, something is finally being done about it.
但代价是要走一些相当极端的路线。
But it means going to some pretty extreme lengths.
正如我之前所说，
Now, as I said earlier,
目前从里昂到都灵确实有火车可坐，
there already is a way to get from Lyon to Turin by train,
只要你不介意乘坐一条建于19世纪的线路——
as long as you don't mind traveling on a line that was built in the 1800s
那条线根本谈不上高速，
and is nowhere near high-speed,
弯道多、坡度陡。
because it's full of winding curves and steep slopes.
更别提山体滑坡了，这在这里是实实在在的威胁。
Not to mention the landslides, which are a very real threat here.
2023年那次滑坡严重到
The one that happened in 2023 was so severe,
整条铁路被迫停运了一年半。
it caused the whole railway to shut down for a year and a half.
当然，自从19世纪以来，
Now, obviously, the way we build our railways
我们建设铁路的方式已经发生了翻天覆地的变化。
has changed massively since the 19th century.
今天的火车不仅更快、更安全、更舒适，
Trains today are not just faster, safer, and more comfortable,
还能穿越那个年代根本无法想象的
but they can get across difficult terrain
险峻地形。
that just wouldn't have been possible all those years ago.
很大程度上，这要归功于新的隧道技术。
Now, a lot of it is down to new tunneling techniques,
而在阿尔卑斯山这里，工程师们已经将
but here in the Alps, engineers have been perfecting an approach
一种地下施工方式打磨到了全新的高度。
that takes underground construction to a whole new level.
这就是所谓的基底隧道——
They're called base tunnels, which comes from the fact
名字来源于它穿越的是山体的基部。
that they burrow right through the base of a mountain.
这意味着轨道可以铺设得几乎完全平坦，
It means the tracks can be laid almost flat,
从而让列车跑得更快、行程更短。
and that enables faster trains and short journeys.
而这正是目前在里昂和都灵之间、
And that's exactly what's under construction in here,
法意边境下方正在建设的东西。
halfway between Lyon and Turin, across the French-Italian border.
全长57.5公里，建成后将成为全球最长的单洞铁路隧道，
Stretching for 57.5 km, it'll become the longest single rail tunnel in the world,
比瑞士的哥达基底隧道略长一点点。
a fraction longer than the Gotthard Base Tunnel in Switzerland.
哥达基底隧道虽然已将近十年历史，
Although that one is almost a decade old,
但至今仍是地球上为数不多建成的基底隧道之一。
it remains one of the only base tunnels to have been completed on this planet.
正因如此，这条蒙瑟尼基地隧道建成后，
Thanks to this, the Mont Cenis Base Tunnel, as it's known,
两城之间的出行时间将从3小时47分
travel times between the two cities are going to be cut
缩短至仅1小时47分。
from 3 hours and 47 minutes down to just 1 hour 47 minutes.
当然，这不只是速度的问题。
It's not just about speed, of course.
新铁路建成后，
Once the new railway is complete,
开车将不再是两地往来的最佳选择。
driving will no longer be the best way to get from A to B.
公路和铁路的货运量预计将趋于平衡，
Those road and rail movements are expected to become a lot more balanced,
几乎达到五五开。
quite literally 50/50.
每年将减少约一百万辆重型车辆上路，
It'll take around a million heavy vehicles off the road every year,
至少目标是这样。
or at least that's the aim.
如果实现，这意味着每年减少一百万吨二氧化碳排放，
If achieved, it would mean an annual reduction of a million tons of CO2,
大约相当于40万个家庭一年的排放量。
which is roughly the same as 400,000 homes produce every 12 months.
货运列车的载货量将从现在的700吨
Freight trains are going to be able to carry 2,000 tons
增加到2000吨。
instead of 700 like they can now.
对乘客来说，每天将有22班长途铁路服务，
And for passengers, there are going to be 22 long-distance rail services every day.
是现在6班的近4倍。
That's up from the six there are right now.
受益的不只是法国和意大利。
France and Italy won't be the only countries to gain from this project.
这条新线路将填补泛欧交通网络
The new line is going to fill a crucial gap
地中海走廊中的一个关键缺口，
in the Mediterranean Corridor of the Trans-European Transport Network.
大大方便欧洲东西方之间的往来，
It's going to make traveling between the east and west of Europe
a hell of a lot easier,
推动经济增长，助力可持续发展。
boosting economic growth and helping sustainability.
但要让这个梦想成真，
But before that dream can become a reality,
还有一些挑战要克服。
there's a few challenges to overcome.
这里就是蒙瑟尼基地隧道法国侧的起点。
So, this is the start of the massive Mont Cenis Base Tunnel
列车将通过下方那段矩形明挖回填法区段进入隧道，
on the French side.
然后进入这段3公里的区段——
Trains are going to enter through a rectangular-shaped cut-and-cover section down there,
这里的地质条件特别复杂。
and then come into this 3-km section,
which passes through some particularly tough geology.
勘测发现，这里的地层充满破碎和错动岩石，
Tests revealed that the ground here is full of fractured and sheared rock,
这意味着这段只能用老办法来施工。
which meant they had to do this section the old-fashioned way.
说的就是传统的隧道掘进方式，也就是钻爆法。
Referring to the traditional tunneling method, otherwise known as drill and blast.
顾名思义，
Well, that, as the name suggests,
就是靠钻孔和爆破来凿通岩石。
involves drilling and blasting your way through the rock.
过程其实挺简单。
The process is quite simple. You
你基本上就是在岩面上钻一圈孔，填入炸药，
basically drill holes in a circle, fill them with dynamite,
按下那个大红按钮，轰的一声炸开，
hit a big red button and blow them apart,
然后用卡车把碎石清走，
clear the rubble out of the way using trucks,
再装上钢拱架来加固周围的岩石，
then put some steel ribs in to reinforce the rock around you,
最后喷上喷射混凝土——类似于喷涂混凝土的混合物，
then spray that with shotcrete, kind of like a mix of sprayed concrete, basically,
就是你现在在我身边看到的这些。
which you can see around me right now.
再往上看，就是山体的岩面。
As well up there is the rock face of the mountain.
这种隧道施工方式最酷的一点
The really cool thing with this type of tunneling method
就是你能亲眼看见你的对手。你
is you actually get to see your adversary. You
能看到面前的岩石，那座你正在与之较量的大山。
get to see the rock in front of you, the mountain that you're battling.
更多的钻孔，更多的爆破，更多的碎石被清走，更多的喷射混凝土，
>> >> More holes, more explosions, more rubble cleared away, more shotcrete,
然后再来一轮，一步一步，一点一点地推进。
and then the same again, step by step, bit by bit.
这只是整个项目的一小部分。
And this is small part of the project.
我们先挖掘了540米的松散地层，
We had 540 m of loose ground excavation,
然后继续用钻爆法推进。
and then we continued on with the drill and blast method.
我们有地面工程，也有地下工程，
We have outside works and inside works.
还有特殊的基础工程和隧道工程。
We have special foundation works and tunneling works.
在项目收尾阶段，我们还需要在这侧完成140米的明挖回填法区段，
And at the end of the project,
这也是这一侧的特殊之处。
we need to do 140 m of a cut-and-cover section,
which is also particular for this side.
就在这里，你才真正感受到自己是在挖穿
So, this right here is where you really feel like you are digging
一座山的心脏。
through the heart of a mountain.
我四周都是冰冷、嶙峋的岩石表面，
I'm surrounded by these cold, craggy rock surfaces,
这是钻爆法留下的痕迹。
which have been left behind by the drill and blast process.
你可以看到已经喷涂了喷射混凝土来帮助稳定洞壁。
And you can see where the shotcrete's been applied to help stabilize the walls.
再往前走一点，这里正在进行的是
A bit further along now, this is the process of converting a tunnel
把隧道从钻爆法留下的嶙峋表面，
from that craggy drill and blast surface you saw
改造成更像常规隧道样子的工序。
to something that looks like a much more conventional tunnel.
设计、构想，然后制造这台设备花了几个月时间——
It took a couple months to design, to imagine, and then to manufacture this this country,
它是一台原型机，在全球范围内都相当独特。
which is a prototype, it's quite unique in the world.
我们每天浇筑10米长的一个仓段，
And we pour a bay of 10 m long every day,
每周工作5天。
5 days a week.
你可以看到前面，他们正在进行这道工序：
You can see ahead of me here, they're doing this process,
先铺设防水膜，就是洞壁上那层厚厚的片材，
this waterproof membrane going in, this kind of thick sheet on the walls,
然后是那种棕红色的钢筋，将来要埋在混凝土里。
followed by that kind of brownish-red steel reinforcement.
接下来是那层厚实的混凝土板。
That's going to sit inside the concrete.
就在这个区段，这套隧道衬砌系统
And then following that, that thick concrete slab.
以每天10米的速度，在阿尔卑斯山下
That tunnel lining system has been laid 10 m a day, every day,
推进了整整3公里。
for 3 km under the Alps in just this section.
不得不说，3公里真的不短，
But it has to be said, 3 km is a long way,
尤其是每次只能做10米的时候。
especially when you're working in 10-m segments.
但这不过是从法国到意大利整个旅途中的沧海一粟。
But that is a mere fraction of the journey from France to Italy.
在这里另一个非常明显的现象，
Another thing that's very visible down here
是在一段隧道完全做好防水之前，到处都湿漉漉的。
is how wet everything becomes before a section of the tunnel is fully waterproofed.
有些地方渗水看起来挺多，
In some places, it looks like a lot,
但对施工负责人来说完全不是问题。
but never enough to concern those in charge of the build.
我们在阿尔卑斯山遇到渗水是正常现象。
And we face in the Alps water ingress, which is normal.
说白了，这对我们来说其实不算坏事，
Basically, this is not bad for us,
因为运输距离很长，
because we have long distances for the logistics,
而且我们喜欢让水留在工作面上，
and we we like the water on the on the surface on the on the piste
这样可以避免扬尘——扬尘在健康和安全方面是个严重问题。
to avoid the dust problems, which is a severe problem for health and safety.
所以说，渗水对我们来说其实挺好的。
So, basically, water is is nice for us.
渗水太多的话，我们用各种抽水系统把水抽出去，
The water which is is too much, we pump it with different different pumping systems.
送到处理厂，
We put it out in a treatment plant.
处理后回收再利用，
We recycle it and we reuse it on the front
用于前方的钻孔和掘进作业。
for the drilling and excavation process.
这类超级工程有一点是百分之百逃不掉的，
One thing mega builds like this are always guaranteed to do,
每次都一样，那就是引发媒体关注。
every single time, is generate headlines.
而那些报道也并不总是一片叫好声。
And they're not always entirely positive.
当你正在穿越一座山的心脏时，
When you're burrowing through the heart of a mountain,
很容易被那些疯狂的施工场面迷住，
it's easy to get caught up in the insane construction
忽略掉那些反对的声音——
and overlook the voices of those who have unfortunately objected to it,
这正是我觉得Straight Arrow News（直箭新闻）特别有用的原因。
which is why I find Straight Arrow News so useful.
很多新闻算法把点击量凌驾于一切之上，
A lot of news algorithms prioritize clicks over everything else,
这让我们很难看到全貌。
which can prevent us from getting the full picture.
来自政治左右两端的文章
Articles from different sides of the political divide
往往对同一件事描述截然不同，
often report things very differently,
而大多数人只能接收到一种声音。
and most of us are only served one side of the story.
Straight Arrow News（直箭新闻）就是专门解决这个问题的。
Straight Arrow News cuts through all of this.
它汇集了来自广泛媒体光谱的内容，无偏见、
You're shown content from a wide spectrum of media free of bias,
无过滤、无炒作，让你能够保持信息畅通，而不被那些多余的噪音干扰。
filter, or spin, meaning you can stay informed without all that unnecessary noise.
我最喜欢的功能之一是"媒体格局"，
One of my favorite features is media landscape,
它会把报道某一特定事件的媒体来源，
which groups sources reporting on a particular story
按照偏见评级从左到右排列出来。
from left to right according to their bias rating.
这让你更容易判断
It makes it much easier to assess
哪些故事被某些群体忽视，哪些被过度渲染。
which stories are being ignored or overly pushed by different groups.
所以，如果你想跳过那些吵吵闹闹，
So, if you like the sound of skipping the drama
直接获取事实，
and just getting straight to the facts,
就去下载Straight Arrow News（直箭新闻）的应用吧。
go ahead and download the Straight Arrow News app.
It
当你们花时间去了解我们B1M的视频赞助商时，
massively helps us here at the B1M
对我们帮助很大，
when you guys take the time to go and check out our video sponsors,
而这一个绝对不容错过。
>> >> and this is one that you definitely don't want to miss.
好了，让我们回到阿尔卑斯山。
Now, let's get back to the Alps.
这条铁路总长270公里。
The railway is going to be 270 km long.
其中70%位于法国境内，30%位于意大利境内。
70% of it sits in France, and 30% of it sits in Italy.
整条线路分为三大部分。
Now, it's divided into three main parts.
跨境区段由主体基底隧道及
There's the cross-border section that consists of the main base tunnel
两侧与现有铁路相连的路段组成。
and the bits either side that connect to the existing railway.
这部分项目
That part of the project
由里昂-都灵欧洲阿尔卑斯隧道公司（TELT）负责监督，
is being overseen by Tunnel Euralpin Lyon Turin or TELT.
这是一家公共推进机构，负责建设和管理工作，
It's the public promoter in charge of the construction and management
法意两国各持有50%的所有权。
with ownership split 50/50 between the French and Italian states.
此外还有延伸至两座城市的路段，
Then, you've got the segments that will run to the two cities,
其中包括若干条隧道，不过长度要短得多。
which include several more tunnels, albeit much, much shorter.
跨境区段总计包含162公里的洞室和隧道，
In total, the cross-border section features 162 km of galleries and tunnels,
包括竖井和安全联络通道。
including shafts and safety bypasses.
超过四分之一的隧道，约50公里，目前已经完工。
Over a quarter of the tunnels, nearly 50 km worth, have now been completed.
基底隧道从圣让德莫里耶纳出发，终点在苏萨。
The base tunnel starts in Saint-Jean-de-Maurienne and ends in Susa.
其中45公里位于法国领土之下，
45 km of it are on French soil, or rather in French soil,
剩余12.5公里位于意大利境内。
and the remaining 12.5 km are in Italy.
由于列车需要双向行驶，
And because trains are going to need to travel in both directions,
实际上有两条管道，一条在北侧，一条在南侧。
there are actually two tubes, one on the north side and one on the south side.
工程量巨大，因此在施工高峰期，
There's loads to be done, which is why
整个项目各工地将有约4000名工人同时参与。
when construction's at its peak, some 4,000 workers are going to be involved
in this project across its multiple sites.
所以，将来如果你乘火车从里昂去都灵，
So, in years to come,
这座小镇将是你看到的法国最后一站，
if you were to take a train journey from Lyon to Turin,
也是你入地深潜之前看到的最后一缕阳光。
this town is the last you'd see of France,
就是这里这座小镇。
the last you'd see of daylight before you headed down
and went deep underground.
就是这里这座小镇。
It's this town right here.
这里已经有一座相当大的火车站，
Now, there's already a pretty big train station here,
但将来它会被一座更大的国际车站所取代。
but in years to come, it's going to be replaced by a much bigger international one.
意大利那端的情况也一样。
And it's the same story down at the other end in Italy, as well.
这样一个宁静祥和的山谷，将成为
A quiet, peaceful valley like this is going to become home
欧洲最重要的基础设施项目之一的所在地。
to one of this continent's most important infrastructure projects.
说到这里，是时候回到隧道里，
Speaking of which, it's about time we got back inside the tunnel
看看剩下的部分是怎么建造的了。
to find out how the rest of it's being constructed.
钻爆法只用于开挖
That drill and blast method is only being used
整条隧道约四分之一的区段。
to excavate around a quarter of the overall tunnel.
其余部分需要另一种可以说更为壮观的技术。
Another technique, arguably even more dramatic, is needed for the rest.
共有七台隧道掘进机（TBM）将同时
In total, seven tunnel boring machines are going to be working away
在阿尔卑斯山下作业。
under the Alps at the same time.
其中一台，也是第一台，名叫薇薇安娜，
And one of them, the first of them, called Viviana,
就在我前方那里。
is just ahead of me down there.
它于2025年9月开始掘进，
It began its journey in September 2025,
任务是挖通全线中9公里长的一段。
and its job is to dig a 9-km stretch of the overall route.
那段路程位于圣马丁拉波尔特和拉普拉茨之间。
That's the part between Saint-Martin-la-Porte and La Praz.
两处都已提前建好了进场隧道，
Access tunnels have already been built in both of these locations,
现在的任务就是把它们打通——
so it's now a case of joining them together,
听起来简单，但正如你所想，其实远非如此。
which, as you might guess, is not as easy as it sounds.
我获得了登上这台隧道掘进机（TBM）的机会，
I've been offered the chance to step on board the tunnel boring machine, or TBM,
它已经取得了相当可观的进展。
which has already been making noticeable progress.
欢迎登上薇薇安娜。这是项目上的第一台TBM，6周前正式启动。
So, welcome on board Viviana. So, it's our first TBM on the project, launched 6 weeks ago.
这是一台独特的机器。
It's a unique machine.
这台机器是一台硬岩TBM。
So, this machine is a hard rock TBM.
这台TBM刀盘的直径是多少？
And what's the diameter of the cutting head of this TBM?
这台TBM的开挖直径是10.4米，
Uh this TBM is 10.4 m excavated diameter.
额定重量2000吨，是的。
2,000 t in nominal mode.
目前大约一半的重量集中在前端。
Yeah. Half of this weight is at the moment is at the front.
刀盘是什么意思？
What do you mean by the cutter heads?
这是机器前脸的另一种叫法，
Well, it's another name for the face of the machine,
由61把刀具组成，在机器穿山掘进时
which is made up of 61 cutters that break up the rock
负责破碎岩石。
as the machine moves through the mountain.
刀盘固定在前端的盾体上。
It's fixed to the section at the front, which is known as the shield.
盾体在运入隧道时，方向与需要掘进的方向成90度角。
This was transported into the tunnel at a 90° angle to the direction it needed to travel.
这意味着在TBM其余部分完全组装好之前，必须先把它旋转到位——
That meant it had to be rotated
因为整台机器不只是靠前面那个负责开挖的部分。
before the rest of the TBM could be fully attached,
because it's not all about the bit that does the actual digging.
刀盘后方，系统的另一部分
Behind the cutter head, another part of the system
负责拼装预制管片，形成隧道的衬砌，
lays the concrete segments that form the lining of the tunnel,
为隧道提供额外的稳定性。
giving it extra stability.
我们的目标是浇筑10万块管片。
We have as a target to cast 100,000 segments.
10万块这种混凝土管片。
100,000 of these concrete segments.
是的。哇。每块管片
>> Yes. Wow. >> So, each of them are
厚50厘米，内置钢筋加固。
50 cm thick.
每8块管片拼成一个环，需要10万块。
They are reinforced with rebar.
Eight of them are sufficient to are needed to to form one ring.
每8块管片拼成一个环，需要10万块。
Yes.
这就让你感受到隧道有多长了，
That shows you how long the tunnel is,
不是吗？
isn't it?
8块拼一环，要做10万块，这太疯狂了。
If you need eight in a ring, you're making 100,000, that's crazy.
再往后，一系列拖车通过传送带
Further back still, a series of trailers help carry
将开挖出的土石运回地面。
the excavated soil and rock back to the surface via a conveyor belt.
这些材料超过一半将在同一个项目中被再次利用。
More than half of that material is being reused on the same project.
其中一部分
Some of it
用于隧道衬砌，
in the tunnel linings,
另一部分则被用于铁路路堤和新火车站的建设。
but it's also finding its way into railway embankments and the new train stations.
所以它的工作远不止挖个大洞。
So, it does a lot more than just dig a big hole.
它本质上就像一座巨型移动工厂，
It's essentially like a giant mobile factory,
这也是为什么需要一整个团队来操作它。
which is why it requires an entire team to operate it.
共有15人协同工作，负责运行和监督
There are 15 people all working together to run and supervise
这台机器的各项功能。
this machine's various functions.
那个红色按钮。我能按一下吗？
>> >> The red button. Yeah, can I press it?
危险的。我能按吗？
>> It's dangerous. Can I press it?
你是B1M的人。
You are from B1M.
好的，现在我们在操控室里。
So, here we are in the control cabin.
这里就是TBM按规定进行操作的地方，
So, that's where the TBM by law operates.
工作人员在这里基本上驾驶TBM、
This is where they basically drive the TBM,
控制掘进方向。
control where it's going.
这里有一系列监控不同设备的屏幕。
A series of of monitors for different devices.
比如这里是机器的导向系统，
For instance, here the the guidance of the of the machine.
这里可以看到千斤顶的压力数值。
And here we can see the pressure into the jacks.
目前压力较低，因为我们现在处于拼装管片模式。
So, here at the moment, the pressure is low because we are now in ring build mode.
所以他说千斤顶现在处于拼装管片模式，
>> So, he thinks these jacks are in ring build mode at the moment,
但在推进掘进时，压力就来了——
but when it comes to pushing forward, that's where the pressure comes,
因为千斤顶要顶住已建好的隧道，把刀盘往前推入地层。
cuz they're pushing back on the tunnel to push the cutting head through the ground.
是的。
>> Yes.
有些地层岩石非常坚硬，所以需要相当大的推力。
And some of that is really tough ground, so you have to push quite hard.
是的，没错。
>> Yes. Yeah.
建造基底隧道，不只是平行钻两条直线那么简单。
Constructing a base tunnel isn't just drilling in parallel lines.
南北两条管道在多处相互连通。
The north and south tubes are linked at several points.
每隔333米，
Every 333 m,
就有一条小通道连接主隧道的
you'll find a small passage connecting the two sides
两侧。
of the main tunnel.
这些通道将用于维护作业，以及在某条隧道需要疏散时作为紧急逃生通道。
They'll be used for maintenance and emergency escape routes in case one of the tunnels needs to be evacuated.
但建造这么长的隧道、
But the problem with building such a lengthy tunnel
又要穿越山体基部，
and doing it through the base of a mountain
最大的难题在于地质条件的不确定性。
is the uncertain geology.
你可能以为他们从一开始就清楚
You might think they would have known from the beginning
掘进过程中会遇到什么样的土层、岩石乃至断层，
what kind of soil, rocks, and even fault lines they're going to find
但实际上你永远无法做到绝对确定，
as they bore through, but you can never be absolutely certain,
即便有今天所有的技术手段也一样。
even with all of today's tech.
最不想发生的事就是：钻了那么远，
The last thing you want to do is drill all that way
结果遇到一个大问题，
and then encounter a major issue
导致工期延误、危及施工团队安全，
that could cause delays, put your teams at risk,
甚至迫使项目整体停工。
or even stop the project entirely.
正因如此，团队不惜花费数年时间，
And that's why teams have incredibly spent years digging exploratory tunnels
在开凿主线之前先挖探勘隧道，
to try and work out what's here
摸清地下情况。
before they go ahead and construct the main routes.
其中一条探勘隧道于2022年完工，为规划人员提供了宝贵的参考信息。
One such tunnel was completed in 2022 to give planners a better idea of what to expect.
每一个时刻，每一个开挖阶段，都可能带来新的意外。
Each moment, each phase of excavation, it can present some new surprise.
我们穿越了80个不同的地质域。
We pass 80 different geological domain.
所以，
So,
地层岩石种类繁多，
a lot of different type of rocks,
从法国侧隧道入口处的冲积沉积物，
from the alluvial deposit at the entrance of the tunnel on the French side
到西阿尔卑斯山最古老的岩石之一，应有尽有。
to the nice, one of the oldest rocks in the western Alps.
这些岩石
These rocks,
对开挖作业的响应和表现也各不相同。
they have also a different behavior and the response to our excavation.
哇。
Woah.
看看这里。
Look at this.
这个空间的体量。
Size of this space.
我们开车进来的时候，工作人员说，
When we were driving down here, the guys were like,
"准备好迎接'大教堂'吧。"
"Get ready for the cathedral."
我当时还在想，"'大教堂'是什么意思？"
I was like, "What do you mean, the cathedral?"
现在我完全明白了。
Now I see exactly what they mean.
我现在已经来到基底隧道的中段，
So, incredibly, I'm now halfway along the base tunnel,
大致处于法国那头和意大利那头的中间位置。
kind of halfway between France down there and Italy down there.
但前方就是隧道掘进技术再次转换的地方。
But ahead of me is where the tunneling technique changes again.
我们将从钻爆法转换过来。
So, we're going from drill and blast.
我身边这个巨大的洞室就是用钻爆法挖出来的。
This huge cavern around me was created by drill and blast.
而前方那面混凝土壁，就是TBM即将开始掘进的起点——
And that concrete face you can see ahead of me up there
这里要掘进17公里，穿越法意边境，
is where the TBM's going to start drilling for 17 km in this instance,
把两国连通起来。
and actually break through across the border from France to Italy,
connecting these two countries.
为了让TBM进入基底隧道，
To give them access to the base tunnel,
共有七个大型洞室正在开挖，最高达22米、最宽达23米。
seven huge caverns, up to 22 m high and 23 m wide, are being excavated.
这些TBM
The TBMs
将在洞室内完成组装。
are then going to be assembled inside.
组装完成后，它们将承担从隧道中段
Once completed, they'll be tasked with digging the long section
一路掘进至意大利边境的艰巨任务。
from the center of the tunnel all the way across the Italian border.
这里即将出发的这台机器，与我们之前见到的那台颇为不同，
Now, the machine that's going to be setting off here quite soon
基本上我们称之为撑靴式TBM。
is pretty different from the one we saw earlier.
Basically, it's what we call gripper TBM.
这些TBM专为硬岩条件下的掘进而设计，
As these TBMs are specially designed to mine
所以不需要
and to go through hard rock condition.
So, there is no precast
像其他项目那样使用预制管片。
segments elements like you have on the other project.
在这里，我们直接掘进，
On this one, we are going to mine,
再根据地质情况，选择喷射混凝土，
and depending on the geology, we are going to either shotcrete
或者安装锚杆和钢拱架来支护地层。
or install like bolts or steel frame to support the ground.
尽管对这个令人叹为观止的工程充满了兴奋，
Despite buzzing with excitement check out this incredible project.
哇，看看这里。
Wow, look at this.
看看这里。
Look at this.
哇，真是太惊人了。
Wow, this is amazing.
我必须说，走进这么深的地下空间，
I've got to say that traveling into a space so far underground
确实让人心生敬畏。
was seriously daunting.
有些地方，我头顶上方有600米厚的实心岩石，
At some points there were 600 m of solid rock above my head,
相当于世界第二高楼默迪卡118大厦的高度。
equivalent to the heights of Merdeka 118, the world's second tallest building.
进入
Heading
隧道时，你会遇到各种提示这里是极端环境的标志，
into the tunnels you encounter all kinds of signs
包括严格的进出人员清点制度，
that this is an extreme environment,
以及每个人都必须佩戴定位标签，以防万一。
including a strict protocol where people are counted in and out of the surface
然后
and have to wear location tags in case the worst happens.
Then
是那段静得出奇的驱车下行，
it's an eerily quiet drive down through rock
穿越那些在某种意义上已经近五亿年
that in a way hasn't seen the world since its formation
未曾见过天日的岩石。
nearly half a billion years ago.
而当你终于抵达深山腹地、
And then when you finally get down to where the action is,
抵达那些施工最热烈的地方时，一切都和"安静"毫无关系。
deep under the mountains, things are anything but quiet.
太不可思议了，真的太不可思议了。
It's remarkable. It is absolutely remarkable.
我站在一座山的下面，
I'm stood under a mountain.
简直不敢多想——
It doesn't really bear thinking about.
那上面压着那么多东西，
There's all that stuff above my head.
而我就在这里。
I'm down here.
这里是一片繁忙的工地。
It's a hive of activity.
男男女女在这里辛勤劳作，
There's men and women working away to connect two countries,
为了连接两个国家、促进经济发展、改变这个世界，
boost economies, and change the world.
真是一件气势磅礴的大事。
It's epic epic stuff.
再往线路深处走，掘进机又被派上了用场。
Further down the line is where boring machines have once again been put into action.
但这些机器看起来和我们之前见到的完全不同。
But these don't look anything like the ones we've already seen.
不是横着穿越崎岖的山地，
Instead of going sideways across the rugged landscape,
这些团队是在垂直向下钻进。
these teams have been drilling straight down.
目前有四口竖井正在施工，
Four vertical shafts are under construction which will go all the way
从海拔1300米的地面一直通向山下的基底隧道，
from the surface, 1,300 m above sea level, to the base tunnel under the mountain.
为隧道提供通风——这在你深入山体数十公里时尤为重要。
They provide ventilation which is especially important
when you're tens of kilometers inside a mountain.
没有通风，空气将无法呼吸，
Without it the air wouldn't be breathable,
无论是对施工人员，
either for the people working on the projects
还是一旦隧道投入运营后需要疏散乘客的情况。
or if passengers need to be evacuated once the tunnels in service.
首先，一个直径约40厘米的先导孔被钻入地下，
First, a pilot hole roughly 40 cm in diameter is bored into the ground
孔径刚好够插入一根金属长杆，一直通到下方的隧道。
just big enough for a long metal bar to be slotted in all the way down to the tunnel.
遇到空洞时，会在内部放置圆筒形金属模板，
Where cavities occur a cylindrical metal formwork is placed inside
将空隙用混凝土填实。
allowing the gaps to be filled with concrete.
然后在底部安装一个刀盘，
Then a cutting head is attached to the bottom
向上钻回地面。
which is used to excavate back up to the surface.
这是一种借鉴自采矿业的技术，所用设备称为反井钻机，
It's a technique borrowed from mining and they're known as raise boring machines,
一种垂直方向的TBM。
a kind of vertical TBM.
其中第一口竖井已经开挖完毕，
The first of these shafts has already been excavated
并使用一种安装于内部的新型机器人完成了临时衬砌。
and covered with a temporary lining using this new type of robot that's placed in sight.
虽然这个项目的大部分作业都在法国境内进行，
While most of the activity on this project has been happening in France,
但意大利那侧的工作也开始提速。
things have started to ramp up on the Italian side as well.
负责生产隧道管片和处理开挖材料的
Preparations are in place for the facilities that will handle the making of the tunnel segments
设施正在筹备之中。
as well as the processing of the excavated material.
基奥蒙泰还新建了一个高速公路立交枢纽，
A new junction of the elevated highway in Chiomonte is also in progress
车辆将通过它进出各施工现场。
which vehicles are going to use to access the sites.
在这个超级工程中，有一点让人无法忽视——
Now one thing you can't help but notice with this mega build
它就坐落在一个美得令人窒息、宁静祥和的山谷里。
is that it's happening in a breathtakingly beautiful, peaceful, and serene valley.
但这种宁静不会持续太久了。
But that's not going to be the case for much longer.
正因如此，许多当地居民一直反对这条铁路的建设。
And because of that, many locals here have been against the railway.
从项目最初立项起，就一直面对着
Since the very beginning the project's faced a backlash
来自抗议团体的强烈反弹，这些团体试图阻止项目推进。
from protest groups looking to put a stop to its progress.
2023年，超过3000名示威者聚集在我所在的这片区域，
2023 saw more than 3,000 demonstrators descend on the area I'm in now,
造成参与者和警察双方均有人员受伤。
resulting in injuries to both participants and police.
他们不满的是新隧道可能造成的环境破坏，
They're unhappy with the environmental damage that they feel the new tunnel will cause,
尤其是里昂和都灵之间本来就已经有一条铁路。
especially as there's already a railway connecting Lyon and Turin.
换句话说，他们认为这条隧道根本没有必要修。
So in other words, they feel it's not really needed.
尽管新线路快得多，承诺了绿色效益，
That's despite the new line being a lot faster, promising green benefits,
而且对进一步山体滑坡的抵御能力也更强。
and having less vulnerability to further landslides.
这一切的造价，也是很多人心中的一根刺。
The cost of all this is another sore point for a lot of people.
目前估算，工程总造价约为250亿欧元，
Current estimates put the price tag at around 25 billion euros,
折合约290亿美元。
which is approximately 29 billion US dollars.
其中近一半由欧盟资金承担，
Almost half of that is being covered by EU funding
剩余部分由意大利出资较多。
while Italy is providing the larger portion of the remaining money.
这主要是因为意大利比法国提前拨付了更多资金，
It's largely because it's committed more of its funding up front than France has,
同时也因为意大利那侧的工程更为复杂。
but also because the Italian side is more complex.
地形更险峻，
The terrain is tougher,
进场路线也更艰难。
the access routes are tougher.
尽管线路更短，工程难度却实实在在地更大。
It's genuinely a lot more difficult despite being shorter.
今天来到这里，你清楚地看到，
When you visit here today you can clearly see
这是一个正处于全面推进阶段的超级工程。
that this is a mega build in full swing.
但这并不是一贯如此。
But that hasn't always been the case.
此前经历过工期延误、来自政界和抗议者的反对，
There have been delays, opposition from politicians as well as protesters,
以及因预算缺口引发的财务不确定性。
and financial uncertainty caused by gaps in the budget.
直到2025年7月，
That was until July 2025
一份新文件获得批准，明确了项目的行动方案和时间表。
when a new document was approved that set out the actions and timetable for the project.
这份由法国、意大利和欧盟共同签署的承诺文件，
A joint commitment from France, Italy, and the EU,
确认了基底隧道的剩余施工计划，
it confirmed the remaining schedule for the base tunnel
预计将于2033年底竣工通车。
which is expected to be commissioned by the end of 2033.
此外，这份文件还促成新铁路各区段
It also resulted in all segments of the new railway
首次全部获得欧盟资金支持。
securing EU funding for the first time.
至于剩余的工程量，还相当可观——
As for what remains on the schedule, it's a lot.
将近四分之三的隧道掘进工作还在待办清单上。
There's almost three quarters of the tunneling work still on the to-do list.
距离目标完工日期当然还有几年时间，
There are of course several years to go until that target completion date,
但在大型基础设施项目的世界里，时间过得很快。
but in the world of big infrastructure projects that can roll around fast.
但现在，基底隧道所有土建施工合同——
But now that all the civil works contracts for the base tunnel,
价值数十亿欧元——已经全部签订完毕，
which are worth several billion euros, have all been awarded,
开挖速度将大幅提升。
the rate of excavation is set to increase significantly.
我们已经把法国和意大利的
We have awarded all the contracts for the construction parts in France
所有施工合同全部签发完毕。
but also in Italy.
我们目前正在签发最后几份设备的总包合同。
And we are awarding right now the final global contracts for the the equipments.
所以我们现在所有土建工程都在同步推进。
So we are now construction all the civil works.
我们也要考虑到一些摆在台面上的挑战——
And we have to to imagine some some difficulties
关于法规、关于各种限制条件。
that that are on the table about the regulation, about the constraints.
当然有施工方面的挑战，
There is some construction difficulties of course,
但也有人的挑战。
but there is a human challenge also.
十年之后，这片迷人的阿尔卑斯山区
One decade from today this charming Alpine region
将比施工期间更加繁忙。
is set to get a lot busier than it's already becoming
with the construction work.
到那时，我们应该能知道答案：
By then we should hopefully know whether sacrificing some of that tranquility
用这片宁静换取整个欧洲的繁荣，
so the whole of Europe can prosper
究竟值不值得。
was the right call to make.
能参与这样一个造福后代、
To work on a a project that is a benefit for the future generation,
有益环境、
that is a benefit for the environment,
还能守护欧洲的项目，
and that you will also save Europe.
我真的打心底里为此感到自豪。
And for me I'm really proud to to work on this project, really.
这个项目让我彻底叹为观止。
>> >> I've been truly blown away by what I've seen on this project.
就像许多大型基础设施项目一样，
Like so many big infrastructure projects,
人们对它的即时效益、以及长远来看是否物有所值，
there are questions here about its immediate impact
都存在疑问。
and whether or not it's going to be worth in the long run.
但不管你怎么看，
For whatever you think of that,
有一点是毋庸置疑的——这个项目将改变我们的世界。
what's undeniable is that this project is going to change our world.
而此刻就在我脚下深处奋战的那些了不起的建设者们，
And the amazing men and women working deep beneath my feet
正在为这一切的实现立下汗马功劳。
at the minute are playing a huge part in making that happen.
等到隧道通车那一天，
For the future when the the tunnel will be open,
我希望能坐上TGV高铁，
when I hope I will take the TGV
然后说一句：这工地，我干过。
and to to say I work on this site.
那将是无比骄傲的事。
It's very proud of it.
这条隧道将让两个大国变得更加紧密相连。
They're going to bring two huge countries closer together.
它将大幅缩短旅行时间。
They're going to cut journey times.
它将让近百万辆货车从公路上消失，从而减少大量排放。
They're going to take almost a million trucks off the road cutting emissions.
这一影响将波及数以百万计的人，
The impact of this is going to be felt by millions of people
远远超出实际使用这条隧道的群体。
far beyond those actually using the tunnel itself.
对我来说，这个项目真正体现了建筑行业最好的一面——
For me this project really does speak to the best of construction.
它展示了我们能做到什么，
It shows what we can achieve
以及我们的工作所能带来的巨大影响。
and the incredible impact that our work can have.
最重要的是，它证明了：
Most of all it shows that whenever this industry
每当这个行业面对看似不可能完成的挑战，
is confronted with something that feels impossible
我们都能让世界刮目相看。
we prove the world wrong.
非常感谢 Straight Arrow News（直箭新闻）对本视频的赞助。
A huge thanks to Straight Arrow News for sponsoring this video.
大家别忘了，如果你想让自己获取新闻的方式变得更好，
Don't forget guys, if you want to improve the way you get your news
就去下载 Straight Arrow News 应用吧，
for the better, go ahead and download the Straight Arrow News app today.
链接就在视频简介里。
The link is down there in the video description.
还有，老规矩——如果你喜欢这个视频，
And as always guys, if you enjoyed this video
想深入了解这个专注于建筑行业的权威频道，
and you want to dig deeper into the definitive video channel for construction,
这个带你走进世界最长隧道的频道，
the channel that takes you into some of the world's longest tunnels,
记得订阅 B1M。
make sure you subscribe to the B1M.
好，这个折法显然是对的吧？
Well that fold that fold's clearly correct, isn't it?
因为看起来就应该是这样的。
Cuz that was That looks like it was meant to be there.
但我们想折成那个形状，
But we want to end up in there,
你干了什么，亚当？
so What have you done, Adam?
哦，这是在开玩笑吧？
Oh, this is a joke, isn't it?
肯定是……不不不，肯定是对的。
That must be No, no, that must be right.
就算押上一百万英镑，
You can have You can say there's a million quid riding on this
我也折不出来。
and I couldn't do it.
我跟你说，我觉得我比之前折得好多了。
I'll tell you what, I think I've done better than it was.
不对，还是不对吧？
No, it's not it, is it?
[哼笑]
>> [snorts]